Hello, today's daf is קסז, Kuf Samech Zayin, 167, and we pick
up with three lines from the top on קסז עמוד א. Kuf
Samech Zayin Amud Alef. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, we're dealing with different
aspects of a שטר Shtar and about corrections or contradictions, and you
go by the bottom line if there's a contradiction. If there's one
letter missing, you can fill it in from the top line. And
now we have the following. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: האי מאן דבעי
למחוי חתימת ידיה בבית דינא לילכי בסוף מגילתא.
Hai man deba'ei lemachvei chasimus yadei beveit
dina lilechei besof megilta. Okay, so somebody wants בית דין Beit Din
to see their signature. Somebody knows that they've signed a lot of
documents and בית דין Beit Din will have to validate their signature,
and so, you know, sometimes they'll be available to come and to
testify on their signature, but sometimes they won't, and maybe other witnesses
won't. So the best thing is you sign a document in front
of בית דין Beit Din and בית דין Beit Din sees your
signature so בית דין Beit Din directly can know of your signature
to validate it. The גמרא Gemara actually has a scenario where it's
necessary to do this. It says let's say ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon signed on a שטר. Shtar. And now שמעון Shimon is dead
and nobody in the world knows שמעון's Shimon signature except ראובן Reuven
and one other person. So how are you going to validate the
שטר? Shtar? Because ראובן Reuven can testify to שמעון's Shimon signature with
this other guy, but then if he testifies to his own signature,
then three quarters of the שטר Shtar is being validated through ראובן's
Reuven testimony. So the way you do it is that he and
this other guy testify to שמעון's Shimon signature because there's no alternative
to that, nobody else knows the
signature. And ראובן Reuven walks in front of בית דין Beit Din
and says, 'Oh, let me try practicing what my signature looks like,'
and he writes his signature, then 'Whoops, I dropped that piece of
paper,' and then he walks away. And בית דין Beit Din goes
ahead and they look at it and now בית דין Beit Din
knows what his signature looks like not through any direct testimony of
his. Okay, so there are ways in which you're going to want
בית דין Beit Din to know your signature so that בית דין
Beit Din can directly validate it. All right, so let's say here's
what אביי Abaye says the following: האי מאן דבעי למחוי חתימת ידיה
בבית דינא, Hai man deba'ei lemachvei chasimus yadei beveit dina, if you
want to show your signature to בית דין Beit Din in order
to get them to be able to validate it in the future,
לילכי בסוף מגילתא, lilechei besof megilta, don't display it or whatever, don't
sign it at the bottom of a piece of parchment. Why? דילמא
משכח לה אחר וכתב דמסיק ביה זוזי. Dilma mishkach lah acher vechasav
demasik bei zuzei. Somebody else will find the piece of paper that
you were just practicing your signature on or demonstrating your signature on
and will write at the top of it, 'I, the undersigned, hereby
borrowed a million dollars from Dov Linzer.' So Michael signs his signature
to בית דין, Beit Din, right? It's like signing a blank check.
Okay, so Michael writes Michael Waksman, stupid enough to write it at
the bottom of a blank piece of paper. So if I find
that piece of paper, I'll just write, 'I, the undersigned, have borrowed
a million dollars from Dov Linzer.' And there you go. ותנן, Utenan,
and we taught: הוציא עליו כתב ידו שהוא חייב לו. Hotzi alav
kesav yado shehu chayav lo. If somebody pulls out a somebody else's
handwritten
note, handwritten IOU, which testifies to the fact that he owes him
money,
גובה מנכסים בני חורין. gova minechasim bnei chorin. So you can use
it to collect, even though it's only one witness. It's a principle
of הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda'as ba'al din keme'ah edim
dami. The person is testifying against himself. Right? That's what every single
check is that we sign. Michael has testified against himself that he
borrowed a million dollars from me. So it can't affect לקוחות, lekuchos,
it can't affect people that bought property from Michael. I wouldn't get
any liens. A, it's not public enough because it's only a person's
individual signature, it's not signed by two witnesses, and B, it's only
Michael's own testimony so he can testify against himself, he can't testify
to hurt the people who bought property from him. But nevertheless, I
can use it to extract money from Michael. And even if the
whole IOU isn't in his handwriting, even if the top of it
is by somebody else, but the signature is in Michael's handwriting, then
it will be good to collect from Michael.
So therefore, don't do that. If you want בית דין Beit Din
to see your signature something
on the side or something like that that's not your handwriting.
Yeah, but this is, I don't know, but you can have like
a pre-printed check and all you need is your signature on the
bottom. Okay, so anyway, so don't go ahead and write your signature
at the bottom of a blank piece of paper. Now we're going
to have a story about this. Okay, ההוא בזבינא, Hahu buzbina, a
certain בזבינא, buzbina, which seems to be the name of a tax
collector, sounds a little derogatory. Anyway, דאתי לקמיה דאביי, da'asei lekamei de'Abaye,
who came to אביי, Abaye, this was like a Jewish tax collector.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him: נחזי לי מר חתימת
ידא, nachzei li mar chasimus yada, could you show me your signature,
what it looks like? Here's a piece of paper, I'd like to
have a sample of your signature. Why? דכי אתו רבנן, De'chi asei
rabbanan, because when רבנן rabbanan come in front of me, the rabbinic
scholars, מחזי לי, machzei li, and if they will show me
a note signed by you that they are like from your school
or something, then מעברנא להו בלא מכסא. ma'avarna lehu belo michsa. I'll
let them pass by without charging them taxes. I'll make a special
deal, אביי, Abaye, I like you so much and I respect Torah
so much
that... exactly. So
אחוי ליה
בריש מגילתא. Achvei lei berish megilta. So אביי Abaye started signing it
at the top of a piece of parchment. There shouldn't be, you
know, it shouldn't be any white space above it. So הוי קנגיד
ליה. Havay kanagid lei.
So the tax collector was like pulling the document to you know
before אביי Abaye signed it, אביי Abaye was getting ready to sign
it at the top, he was like pulling it in order to
get him to sign somewhere in the middle. Right, didn't אביי Abaye
have
it at the end he signs, it's supposed to stay in the
beginning?
Right, that's a good point, but yes, if you basically have if
you have a, you know, I mean if you don't have it
signed but the whole thing is in your handwriting, it's an interesting
question. If I basically wrote, "I, Dov Linzer, hereby borrowed a thousand
dollars from Michael," and didn't sign it, that would probably that's like
כתב ידו, ktav yado, I don't think that needs to be signed,
okay? But if you just have the words "Dov Linzer" and everything
around it was somebody else's handwriting and it wasn't signed, that wouldn't
be good, okay? So clearly the signature has to appear on the
bottom, but it is a good question, let's say, you know, parts
of the text are in your handwriting but not all of the
text. Okay. So anyway so he was trying to get אביי Abaye
to sign in the
middle. So הוי קנגיד ליה, Havay kanagid lei, he was pulling the
document, the piece of paper, to get אביי Abaye to sign in
the middle of this white piece of document. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so אביי Abaye said to him, כבר קדמוך רבנן, Kvar kadmucha rabanan,
the Rabbis already beat you to it, meaning I already have, I
know your tricks, because I know the, you know, we've learned already
in the ישיבה Yeshiva this idea. And the irony is that אביי
Abaye was the one who taught the idea, right? He said to
sign at the top of the document. So whatever, but it means,
you know, okay, the Rabbis are too smart for you, buddy, we
figured this one out a while ago. Okay, fine. So אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, and אביי Abaye also says, מתלת ועד עשרה, Mitlat va-ad
asara, אביי Abaye was a very interesting person, number of teachings to
try to protect you against abuse, okay? So, you know, when you're
writing שטרות, shtarot, מתלת ועד עשרה לא לכתוב בסוף שיטה. Mitlat va-ad
asara lo lichtov besof shita. Don't write at the end of a
line, okay?
So here we are, like "Dov borrowed
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah, Dov, you know, whatever, borrowed from, you know, Michael, and
blah-blah-blah, and" it's at the end of the line, תלת tlat dollars.
Right, almost put in מאות. me'ot.
No,
well that, there's not enough room to put in מאות, me'ot, it's
right at the end of the line.
But you know what
you could put in? תלתין. tlatin. 30. A little יוד yud and
a נון.
nun. Go observe a manuscript, whatever, they often have little
overhangs. So מאות me'ot would obviously be an insertion, but a little
יוד yud and a נון nun you'll be able to get in,
okay? So, you know, so ארבע arba could become ארבעים, arba'im, right?
ארבעים Arba'im or whatever if we were in Hebrew. חמש chamesh becomes
חמישים, chamishim, right? שש shesh
becomes ששים. shishim. שבע sheva
becomes
שבעים. shiv'im. שמונה shmoneh wouldn't work. I wonder why you can't do
שמונה. shmoneh. Maybe because you could do like that? Because it's got
a ה. hei. Anyway, תשע tesha could be תשעים tish'im and עשר
eser could be עשרים. esrim. Okay? So anywhere from three to ten.
Of course שנים shnayim cannot become עשרים esrim and אחד echad cannot
become אחד עשר achad asar or אחדין achadin or something like that.
But anywhere between three and ten though, except שמונה, shmoneh, I have
to think why that works, so maybe they can't turn the ה
hei into a יוד-נון. yud-nun.
So don't write those things at the end of a line, have
room either before the dollars or after the תלת, tlat, exactly.
Exactly, it's assumed that anything else that you'd try to fit in
would get noticed, okay? But okay. So מתלת ועד עשרה לא לכתוב
בסוף שיטה,
Mitlat va-ad
asara lo lichtov besof shita, don't write it at the end of
a line. דילמא מזייף וכתב, Dilma mezayef vechtav, maybe somebody will forge
and, you know, just, you know, multiply it by ten, add in
the יוד-מם. yud-mem. ואי
רמי ליה, Ve-i rami lei, now let's say it happened that it
was at the end of the line and there was nothing to
be done about it. So what do you do? מהדר ליה לדיבוריה
תרי ותלתא זימני. Mehadar lei lediburei t'rei vetlata zimni.
So later in the document write, if you wrote, you know, like
תלת tlat dollars, so later in the document again write, and he
borrowed תלת tlat dollars, and he borrowed תלת tlat dollars, and he
borrowed, write it a few times, okay? Why? And anyway we always
learn from the
last repetition,
okay?
Like we do on a check.
Oh, where we write it in the words and in the numbers,
right.
And we also draw a line.
Exactly, yeah. One wonders why you didn't just say draw a line
here and then write the תלת tlat at the beginning of the
next line. But anyway,
so where was it? תרי ותלתא זימני, Trei vetlata zimni,
one of those times it'll come in the middle of a line.
and there'll be no way to squeeze it in. Okay, now a
story. ההוא דהוה כתיב ביה תילתא בפרדיסא. Hahu d'havei kativ beih tilta
b'pardisa.
So there was a שטר shtar that it was said I sold
selling a third of my orchard to Michael. Okay, אזל azol now
Michael went, knowing how unscrupulous Michael is, מחקיה לגגיה דבית, machkeih l'gageih
d'bet,
he removed the top of the ב bet of the בפרדיסא, bi-pardisa,
וכרעיה v'charaieih
and the and the bottom of it, the foot of it, ושוויה
ופרדיסא, v'shavyeih u-pardisa, so all you were left with was a vertical
line. So basically said I'm selling Michael a third, maybe the context
felt like a third of my garden and the entire orchard, okay,
ופרדיסא. u-pardisa. אתא לקמיה דאביי, Ata l'kameih d'Abaye, came to אביי. Abaye.
Now
אביי Abaye as we know here, אביי Abaye is like aware of
these types of tricks. So אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said
to Michael, מאי טעמא רווח ליה עלמא להאי ו? mai ta'ama revach
leh alma l'hai vav? Why is it that this ו vav has
so much space to breathe? Why is this ו vav so separated
from the word פרדיסא, pardisa, right? Because if it had said בפרדיסא,
bi-pardisa, ב bi
part whatever דיסא, disa, and Michael had done like
this, ופרדיסא, u-pardisa,
why is this ו vav here so much separate from from the
rest of the word, right? Why does it have so much air
to breathe?
Okay, so if Michael's going to forge it, why didn't he just
take up the whole thing, just take בפרדיסא? bi-pardisa? That Michael would
have done that much better. Yeah, wouldn't it be much better?
Maybe I didn't have three פרדיסין. pardaisin. Maybe I only have one.
No, I
have to say all, not whatever.
Okay, so you don't actually have it, you're not then obligated to
go out...
no, that's בבא מציעא אינו מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. Bava Metzia
eino makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam. And whatever it was, but that's
a good question. But presumably, okay, then that would have been a
good trick. Okay, so מאי טעמא רווח ליה עלמא להאי ו? mai
ta'ama revach leh alma l'hai vav? Why is everybody giving so much
space to this ו, vav, does what does he have bad body
odor or something? So כפתיה, kafateih, so he basically he, you know,
he bound and he whatever, he sort of probably like you know
gave some lashings to the the person who was producing this שטר,
shtar, ואודי, v'odei, and he and he admitted that that's what he
had done. He had erased it and forged it. Now of course
the question is, right, what if he hadn't been כפתיה? kafateih? What
if he hadn't? Now what about the גמרא Gemara before that you
can see erasures, you know? Why didn't he, was it not possible
to see the erasure? If it was possible, why didn't he just
invalidate it based on that? Or was it an erasure that wasn't
מקיים mekuyam at the bottom, you know? And this is really not
a helpful story because what if the guy wouldn't have admitted? Maybe
did אביי Abaye פוסל posel it anyway because and based on this
sort of, you know, read, and then the גמרא Gemara is just
showing you that he proving that he was doing the right thing,
but in the end he would have been entitled, like a דיין
dayan is entitled to dismiss a שטר shtar if it seems suspicious?
You know, maybe every now and then there is a שטר shtar
that was written like this and the סופר sofer slipped a little
and gave a little extra space. Right? So like I, you know,
I don't know, how you know what's supposed to be the presumption?
How much is this the discretion of the דיין? dayan? Like that
important question is not being addressed.
Also, okay, what can he do like you know in terms of
corporal punishment and stuff like that?
Yeah, well that's always like בית דין, Beit Din, you know, in
the גמרא Gemara you'd have that often, like the rabbis had problems
had the power to administer lashings or whatever. Individually?
I
don't know, so maybe at a בית דין. Beit Din. But anyway,
that's less interesting to me as to what would be the ruling
if you can't force an admission, you know? Okay. ההוא דהוה כתיב
ביה מנת ראובן ושמעון אחי. Hahu d'havei kativ beih manat Reuven v'Shimon
achei.
So a certain שטר shtar was written that the portion, the field
belonging to Reuven and Shimon the brothers, you know, was sold here
to was sold to this other guy, Mordechai. Okay. הוו להו אחא,
Havu lehu acha, now
Reuven and Shimon had a brother דשמיה אחא, dishmeih Acha, and his
name was Acha. And presumably all three all three of them owned
a different field. So Reuven and Shimon owned field A, all three
brothers owned field B, and field B presumably was a more, you
know, valuable field. So what did this guy do? אזל כתב ביה
ו ושוויה ואחי. Azol kativ beih vav v'shavyeih v'Achi. So rather than
having this שטר shtar say Reuven and Shimon the brother, he bought
Reuven and Shimon the field of the brothers Reuven and Shimon, it
said he bought the field of Reuven and Shimon and אחי. Achi.
Okay, which is a different field. אתא לקמיה דאביי, Ata l'kameih d'Abaye,
he came to אביי. Abaye. אמר ליה, amar leh, מאי טעמא דחיק
ליה עלמא להאי ו? mai ta'ama dachik leh alma l'hai vav? Why
is everybody crowding in
this ו?
vav? The ו vav was obviously squeezed in. כולי האי. kulei hai.
So כפתיה, kafateih, he gave him lashings ואודי, v'odei, and he and
he admitted that he had forged it or whatever. But of course,
again, the question being, and let's say
you can't get the guy
to admit, right?
Is it the judge's discretion to say this looks like a forgery
and I'm not going to do anything about
you know I'm going to tear it up? You know, maybe,
you know, so that's not clear.
Okay, just one second.
So there's a beautiful family of three boys, Shimon, Reuven, and brother.
Right? I don't know, they they used to call somebody Junior. Okay,
anyway, what can I tell you? Okay, so now anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says like this, that's right, he's Junior. Anyway, let me see
what
the how the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק posek about this.
Maybe that'll give us some clarity. י"א Yud Aleph
מלווה
ולווה, Malveh v'Loveh, י"ב. Yud Bet. He call him IRA? No, that's
very funny. IRA, you saw IRA or IRS? Oh, turn around. He's
just... his name is Junior. How hilarious. Okay, let's see what רמב"ם
Rambam says about this. Wait,
how much is it?
Oh, no. כ"ז י"ב, Chaf Zayin Yud Bet, hold on.
Actually, this last case, by the way, saying that you'll recognize the
erasure won't help because you're adding things. Right? The same would be
about this. But say you had a שטר shtar that said 'Closs'
and there was a יוד נון yud nun at the end, and
it looked like it was added in, an overhanging, and maybe a
slightly different script, right?
Would the דיין dayan be within his discretion to dismiss it,
right, if you didn't have it repeated? So
okay, so here's...
so the רמב"ם Rambam says like this. ומתקון השטרות להתבונן בשטר בווין
וזינין שלו שלא יהיו דחוקין בין התיבות שמא זייף והוסיף זו. U'mitikun
hashtarot l'hitbonen beshtar bevavin vezayinim shelo shelo yihyu dechukim bein hatevot shema
zayif vehosif zo. You have to pay close attention, maybe something was
squeezed in. ולא יהיו מרוחקים שמא מחק אות אחת כגון ה' או
ח' והניח רגלה אחת מקום ו' וכן כל כיוצא בזה מדקדקין בו
בכל השטר ובכל
כתב.
V'lo yihyu meruchakim shema machak ot achat kegon heh oh chet vehiniach
ragla achat mekom vav
vechen
kol kayotzei bezeh medakdekin bo bechol hashtar uvechol ktav.
So very, very fine, you know, things that still didn't help. רמב"ם
Rambam says you have to pay close attention if you're the דיין
dayan to see if any of these things happened. And let's say
you think it did, but you can't prove it, right? So again,
it seems like it's the discretion of the דיין, dayan, but it's
not clear.
I have a question. What if you say that the other person's
present in the court and they're saying that's not true? Also the
person whose claim is being held against, he's saying 'I didn't... that
this...'
Well, if the person who is the שטר shtar is hurting admits
that it's accurate text, then it's fine. But he's the one who's
saying it's forged. Right?
No, I'm saying, yes, he's saying it's forged, right? So I mean,
that would bring it to the attention of the דיין. dayan.
Right, that's true, that's true. But again, it still raises the question
of what level of proof is needed. If at the end of
the day... so you're right, he looks at 'Does it look like
it was squeezed in? Does it look like it's the same כתב
ktav or different כתב? ktav? Does it look like there was an
erasure? What is everybody claiming?' So my question is then at the
end of the day, it's completely at the discretion of the דיין,
dayan, right? So good, you look at all that stuff. What is
the threshold of proof necessary? Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ההוא שטרא, Hahu shtra, there was a שטר, shtar, דהוה
חתים עליה רבא ורב אחא בר אדא. Dehava chatim aleih Rava v'Rav
Acha bar Adda. רבא Rava and רב אחא בר אדא Rav Acha
bar Adda were signers of it. אתא לקמיה דרבא, Ata l'kamei d'Rava,
it came to רבא Rava himself as a דיין, dayan, and he
himself would have been a signer. That's an interesting question of עד
נעשה דיין. ed na'aseh dayan. But anyway, the גמרא's Gemara not going
to go there. אמר ליה דין חתימת ידא דידי, Amar lei dein
chatimat yada didi, yes, this is my signature. מיהו קמי דרב אחא
בר אדא לא חתמי לי מעולם. Mihu kmei d'Rav Acha bar Adda
lo chatmi li mei'olam. I know that I never co-signed a שטר
shtar with... whoever this was, רב אחא בר אדא. Rav Acha bar
Adda. Pretty amazing to know that you... but well, how would you
know that somebody, these two rabbis who knew each other, presumably people
were asking rabbis to be their witnesses, how would you think that
the two rabbis had never co-signed? How did רבא Rava know he
never co-signed with this rabbi? Anyway, כפתיה ואודי, Kafteih v'odei, so they
basically he forced him and he admitted that he forged it. So
now he forged it, but רבא Rava himself was fooled about his
own signature. So אמר ליה Amar lei he said to him, בשלמא
דידי זייפת, Bishlama didi zayafta, maybe okay, maybe you're a great forger
and you were able to forge my signature. אלא דרב אחא בר
אדא, Ela d'Rav Acha bar Adda, but how did you forge רב
אחא בר אדא's Rav Acha bar Adda signature? דריתי ידיה, D'retiti yadeih,
his hand's like shake, like maybe he has, you know, Parkinson's or
something, or he's just very old. היכי עבדת, Heichi avdat, how were
you able to replicate his signature with such a shaking hand? אמר
Amar he said, אנחי ידי אמיצרא. Anchi yadai amitzra. Okay, what I
did was I put my hand on a rope that... like a
walking bridge. And you know, as people were walking on the bridge
and the rope was like, you know, jiggling or whatever, it was
moving, I was signing it as I had my hand on the
rope. ואמרי לה V'amri lah some say, קם אזנוקא וכתב. Kam aznuka
vechatav. I was hanging, I supported... I hung myself, whatever, like I
suspended myself from a rope of a... on a pail in a
well, you know, which is sort of like swinging. And as I
was doing that, I was signing. So you see, people will go
to great lengths to forge signatures, and some people are very expert
at it. I have a question.
If they already have the קיום kiyym of בית דין, Beit Din,
could you... would that have gotten off the ground?
Sure! I mean, what are you going to do at the end
of the day? If there's a good forger, there's a good forger.
What are you supposed to do?
No, I'm saying is if they... because part of it is that
once the בית דין Beit Din מכיימ'ס mekayems the signatures, it's sustained.
Oh, the בית דין Beit Din was mekayem it, and
then the person has to say that 'Oh, it's my signature...'
No, then it would probably be too late, right? No, then it
would be, well, yeah, I mean, then it would be right, probably
after קיום, kiyum, if the guy, well, if the guy himself admitted
he's forfeiting his claims, you know, but, but,
no meaning like, but meaning if
let's say I don't know, let's say two witnesses came and said
we saw this guy forge this document.
I'm going to know, you know, you're whoever it is, I
understand, and you admit
in, you know, there they say wait a minute, I never signed
this, right, like you know with this guy, that can't be my
signature. Right.
Is it, oh, different people who are admitting? If רבא Rava says
he never signed it after it's מקוים mekuyam in בית דין, Beis
Din, that's probably the signature says he's never signed it, that's probably
כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד keivan shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid
even though he, right, he doesn't have, it doesn't seem like, those
are all very good questions. It does not seem like the person
who signed has greater נאמנות, ne'emanus, you know, once his signature has
been מקוים, mekuyam, you know, if witnesses validated his signature and it's
been מקוים, mekuyam, it doesn't seem like he has greater נאמנות ne'emanus
to override that. What you're asking though is, I don't know, let's
say other people came and said that we saw so and so
forge the document, right? Would that sort of be like עדים שנמצאו
זוממין? eidim she-nimtzu zomemin? You know, it's sort of like saying עמנו
הייתם במקום פלוני, imanu hayitem bemakom ploni, right? It's a type of
a way of saying that, right? Or let's say the guy himself
admits that he forged it after it was מקוים, mekuyam, right? That's
a good question. I don't think
the signatory himself has, you know, נאמנות ne'emanus once his signature has,
that's like a כיון שהגיד keivan shehigid type of a question. But
you're right, it's like finding a פסול, psul, an external פסול psul
in the עדים eidim type of a thing, yeah.
מצרא Meitzara has the same שורש shoresh as מצרים. Mitzrayim.
That is true. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
משנה. Mishnah. Yes?
I don't know if that's what you intended, that he says he
would not sign before the other Rabbi added his signature.
Oh! Oh, לקמיה! lekamei! Oh, what did he say? אנה
לקמיה?
Ana
lekamei? Oh, that's a good point. Prior to רב אחא, Rav Acha,
not in the presence of. Oh, I wouldn't have signed, I wouldn't
have put my signature first. Oh, that's a better פשט. pshat. That
explains why he knew that. Okay, so let's see what the next
גמרא: Gemara: כותבין גט לאיש אף על פי שאין אשתו עמו. Kotvin
get l'ish af al pi she-ein ishto imo. The next משנה. Mishnah.
So now we move away from forgery, I mean it's still somewhat
related, is there concerns of abuse of the שטר, shtar, but it's
less about the actual script and words and the possible erasures and
forgeries. You can write a גט get for a man even though
his wife isn't there because, you know, it's a unilateral thing, you
don't need his wife's agreement, he'll pocket the גט get and he'll
give it to her when he's ready to divorce her.
Now, he would also have to authorize it.
Well, he means he has to authorize it. Now, תוספות Tosafos has
a question, which is what about the fact that if he gives
it to her a few months later and it makes it look
like they were divorced earlier, that there will be implications. Like, first,
an implication is, you know, she could commit adultery and get the
גט get later, make it look like she was divorced earlier, but
you know, that at least is like, alright, whatever, you know, what
are we going to do about that? But the bigger concern here
is protecting the לקוחות, lakochos, because if he goes ahead and gives
it to her later, then it'll look like she was entitled to
the פירות peiros of the field for the last few months, when
actually he was the one that was entitled, and then people who
bought the fruit from him, you know, could be swindled. Alright, so
תוספות Tosafos deals with that problem. Maybe I'll just read one line
of his answer, the תוספות אף על פי. Tosafos af al pi.
תוספות Tosafos is like this:
He says, ואומר ר"י, ve-omer Ri, three lines before the lines get
wide: ואומר ר"י דלא מקיש איניש פורענותא לנפשיה. ve-omer Ri d'lo makish
inish pur'anusa l'nafshei.
We assume that a person is not going to, you know, to
arrange for a גט get to be written well before it's being,
you know, the time that he's going to give it. Like it's
a bad סימן siman as it were, you know, oh, you're getting
divorced or whatnot. So if you're doing it, it's because you're about
to give the גט. get. הלכך היכא דאשכחית רעיה דדוקא חיישינן. Hilkach
heicha d'ashkechit re'ia dedavka chayshinan.
If there's a reason to suspect, like the גט get was found
on the floor, then we start worrying. Oh, maybe it was found
on the floor, maybe it had been written much earlier and whatever,
because things are looking a little fishy. והכי אמרינן בפרק קמא דגיטין
דלא מקיש איניש פורענותא לנפשיה שיכתוב לו גט קודם שירצה לגרשה. Ve-hachi
amrinan b'perek kama d'Gittin d'lo makish inish pur'anusa l'nafshei sheyichtov lo get
kodem sheyirtzeh l'gareshah. In general we're not concerned about that, we assume
it'll be given very quickly. If there is reason to suspect, things
will start, we'll start suspecting. But as a general rule we're not
concerned about that. And then he says: וגיטי הבאים ממדינת הים, ve-gittei
habaim mimedinas hayam, right, there's always a question. If you learn the
beginning of גיטין, Gittin, it starts with the idea of a גט
get that's sent from overseas. So that גט get is always going
to be way predated, right? Even if it was dated, right, because
it's going to take half a year to get it. So how
are you going to know, we're going to think the woman was
divorced, you know, earlier than she was? So it says: לא, קלא
אית להו. lo, kala is lehu. Those types of things, because they
had to get conveyed and done in front of a בית דין
Beis Din and the whole thing, you know, people know that they
were written much earlier and given only later. Okay, so back to
the משנה. Mishnah.
Could somebody write in the גט, get, they know that it's going
to take three months and they say I'm writing this on this
date but it's to take effect when it arrives in three months?
Well,
you could write in a גט get that it should take effect
three months from now, that you could definitely do. You could give
the גט get today and say it's going
to
take... but
you're not required to do that. Okay, so כותבין גט לאיש אף
על פי שאין אשתו עמו, kotvin get l'ish af al pi she'ein
ishto imo, you can write to the man, והשובר לאשה. v'hashover l'isha.
Now after the woman gets paid her כתובה, ketubah, she will either
can either give, you know, give the גט get back to the
husband and the husband can tear the גט get so that won't
serve as an evidence that she's owed the כתובה, ketubah, I mean
or give the כתובה ketubah back to the husband and the husband
will tear the כתובה, ketubah, or if she says she doesn't have
the כתובה ketubah or she doesn't want to give it back, she
can write a receipt to the husband, I hereby am, you know,
have received full payment of my כתובה. ketubah. So let's say the
woman goes to court and says, can you please write for me
a receipt? I'll give it to, he hasn't paid me my כתובה
ketubah yet, but I'll give it to him once he pays me
the כתובה. ketubah. So sure, be my guest, have a receipt. Worst
case happens is it'll slip out of her, you know what I
mean, like she's only hurting herself, right, if he hasn't paid the
כתובה ketubah and she's going to give it to him before he
paid the כתובה, ketubah, it's only going to hurt herself. So you
can write it for him אף על פי שאין בעלה עמו, af
al pi she'ein ba'alah imo, ובלבד שיהו מכירין, uvilvad sheyehu makirin,
but they have to, the scribe have to recognize the parties. So
which parties do they have to recognize? We'll discuss both parties, only
the one who's authorizing, we'll discuss about that in the גמרא. gemara.
והבעל נותן שכר, v'haba'al noten sachar,
the husband has to pay, you know, it's like who pays the
court fees? So whether for the גט get or the שובר, shover,
the husband has to pay the fees. Okay now we're going to
see why, the reason, the basic rule is the beneficiary pays the
fees. So why he pays the fees of the שובר shover is
obvious, he's the beneficiary, the receipt basically says that he now, you
know, he doesn't owe his wife any money anymore. Why he pays
the receipt of the of the כתובה ketubah of the actual גט,
get, excuse me, why he pays the scribal fees, thank you, okay,
of the גט get we'll have to see, because it's not so
clear who do we identify as the beneficiary.
Well, I mean part of it would be then she's not fully
מגורשת, megureshet, you might say like, I
understand, alright, we'll see in the גמרא. gemara. I
understand. כותבין שטר ללוה אף על פי שאין מלוה עמו, kotvin shtar
l'loveh af al pi she'ein malveh imo, I can get the סופרים
sofrim to write a שטר shtar that I borrowed a thousand dollars
from Michael even though Michael isn't around, I mean I'm only hurting
myself, why should Michael mind that I'm getting them to write that
שטר? shtar? אף על פי שאין מלוה עמו. af al pi she'ein
malveh imo. ואין כותבין למלוה עד שיהא לוה עמו, v'ein kotvin l'malveh
ad sheyehe loveh imo, but Michael can't go to the סופרים sofrim
and say write a שטר shtar that דב Dov borrowed a thousand
dollars from me. Why would they do that? Maybe he's lying, they
would only do that if I was, it was in my presence
and I was authorizing it. והלוה נותן שכר, v'haloveh noten sachar, and
the לווה loveh is the one that gives the pays the fees.
Why? Because the לווה loveh is the beneficiary of the transaction, he's
not the beneficiary of the שטר, shtar, but he's the beneficiary of
the transaction. He gets money and it doesn't cost him anything, he
doesn't pay interest, right? So he is a total beneficiary. So the
one who's the beneficiary, again not of the, you know, of the
transaction is the one that pays for the fee. והלוה נותן שכר.
v'haloveh noten sachar. כותבין שטר למוכר אף על פי שאין לוקח עמו,
kotvin shtar l'mocher af al pi she'ein loke'ach imo, you write a
שטר shtar for the seller even though the purchaser isn't there, right,
so basically Michael can have them write a שטר shtar that he
sold his car to me even though I'm not there, why should
I mind if he's writing that? ואין כותבין ללוקח עד שיהא מוכר
עמו, v'ein kotvin l'loke'ach ad sheyehe mocher imo, but don't write it
for the buyer unless the seller's there. והלוקח נותן שכר, v'haloke'ach noten
sachar, the buyer there is the one that pays the fees, he's
considered the beneficiary of the transaction. Why is he? The מוכר mocher
gets money, but anyway, I
can't write the שטר shtar that you bought my car for a
thousand dollars, right, then I can not give you the car,
then you'll give me that thousand dollars for the car, then where's
the car? I don't know, I don't know what you did with
it.
No, no, no, no, the שטר shtar only means something if it's
in the hands of the one who bought it. The שטר shtar
is just evidence for the person who bought it that he bought
it.
Okay, I mean, exactly, right, exactly.
I mean you have it signed but it's not effective until it
goes over to the other side. אין כותבין שטר אירוסין ונישואין אלא
מדעת שניהם. ein kotvin shtar eirusin v'nisuin ela mida'at shneihem. Now a
שטר אירוסין shtar eirusin which is basically our תנאים, tenaim, how much
each side is going to commit or how much or what will
be the penalties if they don't see their kids to the חופה,
chuppah, so that has both, there are two parties to that, there's
not only one party, by both sides are beneficiaries and obligating themselves,
or a שטר נישואין shtar nisuin which is a כתובה, ketubah, that's
also seen as having both sides sort of as beneficiaries or as
part equal parties. So in that case it needs to be authorized
by both sides. והחתן נותן שכר, v'hachatan noten sachar, and there the
groom is the one however who pays. Why is the groom pay
if both sides are seen as you know equal parties? So we'll
see. אין כותבין שטר אריסות וקבלנות אלא מדעת שניהם. ein kotvin shtar
arisut v'kablanut ela mida'at shneihem. Now, now we're getting to contracts, okay,
so contracts as opposed to a bill of sale, right, a contract
actually clearly has the you know responsibilities and obligations in both directions.
So if you have a שטר shtar that basically is a case
of a sharecropping, that's אריסות, arisut, or קבלנות kablanut which is a
case of contracting for a job. job, so in those cases you
have both of them have to agree to it. Right, it has
to say, like here is the job and here is how much
you agree to get paid. Right, so therefore you need both parties
there, like if I basically have a thing that says that Eli
there agrees to mow my lawn for $2, and I'll say, write
it without Eli being around, he's like, what the heck are you
talking about, right? Like how are we writing with Eli being around?
He wouldn't necessarily agree to those terms. All right. So,
המקבל
נותן שכר. ham'kabel noten sachar. The one who is taking the job
is the one who pays, because even though again both parties sort
of obligate and benefit from, okay, it's really seen as like the
one who is getting the job is, he's the one more in
need as it were. So he's the one that pays the fees.
אין כותבין שטרי בירורין ein kotvin shitrei beirurin וכל מעשה בית דין
v'chol maaseh beit din אלא מדעת שניהם. ela midaat sheneihem. If there's
some שטר shtar about like how a court was picked or or
some type of a court document that affects both parties, both litigants,
so you have to get both parties to basically, like, agree to
it. I guess, well, sometimes the court will write because of their
judgment, then the parties don't have to agree, the parties were just
there. But some type of a document that is done in court
that has all that requires all parties to agree, you have to
get them all there, ושניהם נותנים שכר, ush'neihem notnim sachar, they both
pay for it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer, לשניהם כותבין שנים, lishneihem kotvin shenayim, לזה לעצמו ולזה לעצמו. l'zeh
l'atzmo ul'zeh l'atzmo. Right, that's an important question, because all these שטרות
shtarot that affect both parties, that are two-sided שטרות, shtarot, not one-sided
שטר, shtar, you would want two copies. Each side would want a
copy, right? So he says, okay, you make two copies. Right, but
how we didn't say that before? How about when I got the
שטר shtar that said Eli's mowing my lawn for $2? Okay, who
gets that שטר? shtar? Which side gets it, right? Do both sides
get it? So that is not really spelled out. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי? mai? ובבדא דמכירין. uv'vada d'makirin. מכירין.
makirin. You can only write this שטר shtar for the גט get
for the man without his wife there if they recognize him. So
who are recognized? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav, ובבדא דמכיר שם האיש בגט ושם האשה בשובר. Uv'vada d'makir
shem ha'ish b'get v'shem ha'isha b'shovar. You don't have to recognize both
parties. In the case of the גט, get, let's just focus on
the גט, get, but the parallel would be the case of the
receipt. They recognize that this is the man. ראובן Reuven Jacobson comes
to them,
ראובן Reuven Jacobson comes to them, you get that, ראובן Reuven Jacobson?
Okay, comes to them and says, like write a גט get for
my wife, שרה. Sarah. They have no idea who his wife is,
that that's her name or whatever, but
they know this guy, they recognize him, so that's okay. They don't
have to recognize שרה. Sarah. Because what's the concern? I mean, he's
only telling, as long as we know it's him, if he's got
a wife by the name of שרה, Sarah, he'll use it. If
he doesn't have a wife by the name of שרה, Sarah, he
can't use it. So why should what's the downside? We'll write it
without knowing שרה. Sarah. The same the woman comes in front of
us. שרה Sarah says, write this receipt for my husband,
the שובר shovar for my husband, ראובן Reuven Jacobson. So they know
her name is שרה. Sarah. They don't know who her husband is.
But what's the downside? If she's got a husband by that name
and he pays her and she gives him the receipt, good. And
if she doesn't, it's not going to do anybody any whatever, it's
going to say that her כתובה ketubah was paid, but
who else would it relate to other than her husband? So what
should be the downside? That's what the גמרא Gemara initially thinks. ובבדא
דמכיר שם האיש בגט uv'vada d'makir shem ha'ish b'get ושם האשה בשובר.
v'shem ha'isha b'shovar. יתיב רב ספרא ורב אחא בר רב הונא ורב
הונא בר חיננא, Yativ Rav Safra v'Rav Acha bar Rav Huna v'Rav
Huna bar Chinena, יתיב אביי גבייהו. Yativ Abaye gabaihu. So these three
rabbis were sitting and אביי Abaye was with them. יתיב וקמיבעיא להו,
Yativ v'kamiba'aya lehu, and they asked the following question. שם האיש בגט
אין שם האשה לא? Shem ha'ish b'get in, shem ha'isha lo? שם
האשה בשובר אין שם האיש לא? Shem ha'isha b'shovar in, shem ha'ish
lo? They only need to recognize the man's name in the גט,
get, not the woman's
name? They only have to recognize the woman's name in the receipt
and not the man's name? וליחוש שמא כתב גיטא? V'lichosh shema katav
gita? So now we're going to ignore the שובר shovar case. You
can flip it by the שובר, shovar, but let's focus on the
גט, get, which is more consequential anyway, and let's talk about the
possible downside. So they went ahead and they wrote this גט get
for ראובן Reuven Jacobson without knowing whether his wife's name really was
שרה Sarah or not שרה. Sarah. So here's the concern.
וליחוש, V'lichosh, why aren't we concerned, דילמא כתב גיטא? dilma katav gita?
He got them to write this גט get and his wife's name
wasn't שרה, Sarah, but there was another ראובן Reuven Jacobson in the
town whose wife's name was שרה. Sarah. And what did he do?
ואזיל וממטי ליה לאיתתיה דהאיך. v'azil u'mamtei lei l'ititei d'haich. He gave
this גט get to this שרה, Sarah, not his wife, the wife
of this other ראובן Reuven Jacobson, וזימנין דאזלה וגביה לכתובתה. v'zimnin d'azla
v'gavya l'ktubatah.
And therefore she will claim she's divorced when she wasn't divorced, and
maybe she'll collect her כתובה ketubah without having to whatever the reason
is that she's doing it, she pays him a nice fee, she
finds this guy, her husband, she wants a גט get from her
husband, her husband won't give her a גט, get, she finds another
guy who's known to the court who has the same name as
her husband and gets him to get the court to write a
גט. get. They don't know that his wife's name isn't שרה, Sarah,
and he goes ahead and he gives it to this woman. Woman.
And similarly what?
What? He doesn't have to sign on it. וזימנין דאתיא Vezimnin de'asya
times, אזלא וכתבא אשה שובר, azla vekhasva isha shover, the woman will
go ahead and get a receipt written, and the court won't know
whether this is her husband's name or not, it's not her husband's
name. ויהיב לגברא Veyaiv legavra now,
he gives to a guy who she told the court her husband's
name was, you know, you know, Fred Smith. And she goes ahead
and it's not her husband's name, but she goes ahead and she
gives it to a Fred Smith whose wife has the same name
as she does. And now this Fred Smith doesn't have to pay
the wife the כתובה kesuva and gives her a little bit of
a kickback. Okay. ויהיב לגברא דלאו דילה Veyaiv legavra delav dila and
gives it to a man that's not her husband. So I don't
get it, they say, how do you allow it without knowing both
parties' names? So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, Abaye said back,
you know what, you're right. הכי אמר רב, Hachi amar Rav, שם
האיש בגט והוא הדין לשם האשה. shem ha'ish beget vehu hadin leshem
ha'isha. You're right. They do have to recognize both parties' names. It
says the woman's name and the man's name.
שם האשה בשובר והוא הדין לשם האיש, Shem ha'isha beshover vehu hadin
leshem ha'ish, the woman's name in the
receipt and the husband's name. Okay, so that should solve it, except
what
about the case where you have two couples whose wives' names and
the husbands' names are both the same?
So the גמרא Gemara says, וליחוש לשני יוסף בן שמעון הדרים בעיר
אחת, veleychosh lishnei Yosef ben Shimon hadarim be'ir achas,
two Yosef ben Shimons in the same city. Now, of course, the
funny thing here is, you know, the whole sort of feminist critique
about how like it's always about men and the women are never
noticed and so on. We already were dealing with a case of
שני יוסף בן שמעון הדרים בעיר אחת. shnei Yosef ben Shimon hadarim
be'ir achas. What the גמרא Gemara is concerned about here is not
just שני יוסף בן שמעון הדרים בעיר אחת, shnei Yosef ben Shimon
hadarim be'ir achas, but it's שני יוסף בן שמעון הדרים בעיר אחת
shnei Yosef ben Shimon hadarim be'ir achas whose wives also have the
same names. Right, but that's not even mentioned. That is the whole
question, but that's not even mentioned as part of describing the problem.
The whole problem here is two couples where the husbands and wives
both have the same names. So how do we prevent against that?
Now תוספות Tosafos has a long discussion before we get to the
answer about the question about like maybe a שטר shtar would never
be good. Because if a שטר shtar is only good because it
or גט get let's say, because it testifies to the story it's
telling, and in this city there are two people who have that
man's name, two couples with the same husband's name and wife's name,
so maybe the whole שטר shtar is פסול. pasul. Regardless, even if
it's not forged, it's פסול pasul because it's not clear what story
it's telling, right? Maybe you either need עדי מסירה edei mesira or
you need a third generation or a family name. So תוספות Tosafos
deals with that issue because there's another גמרא Gemara that makes it
sound like that if it could be telling the same story about
two different sets of people, two different couples, and you don't know
which one, then maybe that's intrinsically a פסול pasul גט. get. Okay,
but we're not dealing, we're going to bracket that for now. The
גמרא Gemara is just going to worry about the misuse of it.
So the גמרא Gemara says, why don't we concern about שני יוסף
בן שמעון הדרים בעיר אחת? shnei Yosef ben Shimon hadarim be'ir achas?
דילמא
כתב גיטא ואזל ומטי ליה לאיתתא דהאיך, Dilma kasav gita ve'azal umati
lei le'itata deha'ich, and this one will write a גט get and
give it to the other man's wife? Same problem. Okay, so but
maybe both of them, meaning even if you recognize both names, right,
the question is now we're asking the question on the משנה. mishna.
The משנה mishna said you could write it to the husband without
the wife being present. So what this is saying is no, we
shouldn't allow that. Even if we know all the names are right,
maybe he'll give it to the other couple. And why don't we
insist that the woman be present and that the גט get be
given in our presence?
Okay, on the רישא reisha of the משנה, mishna, not on the
next part.
Yeah, even if you're מכיר makir everything. How do we recognize, how
do we do it without the wife being present?
בלא עמה. Belo ima.
Maybe you've got a whole scam going on. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר להו רב אחא בר רב הונא הכי אמר רב, amar
lehu Rav Acha bar Rav Huna hachi amar Rav, here's what רב
Rav says, שני יוסף בן שמעון הדרים בעיר אחת, shnei Yosef ben
Shimon hadarim be'ir achas, if we know that they're both that there
are two couples with the same names, okay, if we don't know
there's only so much we can do if we don't know. But
if we do know that there are two couples with the same
names, אין מגרשין נשותיהן אלא זה בפני זה. ein megarshin neshoseihen ela
ze bifnei ze. Okay, they can only divorce their wives, you know,
in the presence of one another. So
basically
if you want to divorce your wife and there's another man and
woman with the same name, we're going to have to get them
to come to בית דין, beis din, right, for the act of
your divorcing your wife. Now it's not exactly immediately clear to me
why that solves the problem. Because here I am, I'm ראובן בן
שמעון, Reuven ben Shimon, I say write a גט get for my
wife, and yeah, when I divorce her, I'll get the other couple
to be present. Okay, I mean I tell you that, I don't
have to divorce her right now, I still will not do that.
Okay, and sure, when I divorce her, I'll make sure the other
couple's present. And then I go ahead and I give the גט
get to the other woman, to the wife of the other man.
She goes ahead and she brings it to the court and she
says I was divorced and she says oh, they say wait a
minute, but there's another couple with that name. She says fine, yeah,
they were both everybody was there when I got the גט. get.
So, right, I mean how are we going to disprove that? Like
what's the point? At the end of the day, she's still going
to try to prove she's divorced by by presenting a גט. get.
Are we going to say since we know, the גט get is
not sufficient evidence and you need to go ahead and bring us
the witnesses that were there and the witnesses have to testify that
both couples were there? Yeah. I don't... I still don't understand, why
don't we just... if that's true, why don't we just say if
there's two יוסף בן שמעוןs Yosef ben Shimon הדין בעיר אחת hadayin
be'ir achas when when a woman presents a גט, get, we need
to have the witnesses come in and come in person and testify?
I don't understand what it accomplishes by having the other couple there.
She's still going to claim that she was divorced by producing the
גט. get.
First of all, they're not writing the גט get right there, they've
already written the גט, get, it's just a matter of coming to
the בית דין Beit Din and...
No, they're writing the גט get for the man without his wife
being there.
Yeah, right. So but... I read this as the assumption a person's
not going to lie in court. Like in other words...
Of course he is, that was our whole concern.
No, no, you're dealing with fraudsters
anyway, yeah.
What?
The concern was they weren't there, so it's a tough another matter
to have people come to בית דין Beit Din stand before the
judges and actually boldly lie.
But that was what we've been assuming.
Was this assumed to be the case and the wife displays a
גט, get, the court will insist she bring witnesses who can testify
that both of them were present. Any foul play will be precluded.
So if what we're really saying is that if we know that
there are two יוסף בן שמעוןs Yosef ben Shimon she has to
bring in witnesses, just say she has to bring in witnesses! I
still don't understand what's accomplished by demanding that the other couple have
been present. At the end of the day, we're solving the problem
by saying we're not going to trust the גט. get. We're going
to insist that she bring in witnesses who saw it. So then
why do we have to have both parties, both couples present? What,
maybe the witnesses themselves didn't know that this wasn't her husband?
Maybe. But the real answer is that we're going to insist on
witnesses come and we're not going to rely on the גט get
in that case. So, I mean, people hearing my point? It doesn't
matter what we claim is necessary in the giving of the גט,
get, in the end she's producing the גט get and she's making
a claim about what happened. So the real point is we're going
to insist that witnesses come and tell us what happened. Okay? But
if that's true, it's not exactly clear to me why you need
the other couple there.
Is it involved at the end when she comes or in the
writing?
Need to be done anyway now in front of בית דין. Beit
Din. Right, at the writing in צפת Tzfat there are witnesses present.
Then she comes with a גט get that has a signed גט,
get, normally we say that גט get is fine. Now we're saying
no, no, if we know there are two יוסף בן שמעוןs, Yosef
ben Shimon the גט get won't be fine, we'll need witnesses to
come. And the witnesses are not just going to have to say
they saw the husband give the גט, get, they're going to say
the other couple was there as well. Maybe, anyway, maybe it's to
prevent a case where the man claims he's her husband and the
witnesses don't know any better. All right, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara
continues, okay? אימא דאזיל לעיר אחרת, Eima de'azil le'ir acheret,
maybe this guy will go to a different city ומיחזי ליה שמה
ביוסף בן שמעון. umichzei lei shemeih beYosef ben Shimon.
His name isn't יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. His name is
Jacob Jacobson. Okay? But he goes to Sefardi... but he goes to
another city and he starts calling himself יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben
Shimon and when they ask him, oh, a guest, what's your name?
We'll give you an עליה, aliyah, okay? And he starts calling himself
יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. So now what does he do?
וכתב גיטא. vekhateiv gita. And then he goes to a סופר sofer
after he's managed to pull this off and he says, you know,
I come from this other city, from Vilna, go ahead and write...
my name is יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon, go ahead and
write me a גט get and so on, okay? And he writes
a גט. get. Now in that case, when he gets back to
the city and gives the גט get to יוסף בן שמעון's Yosef
ben Shimon wife and יוסף בן שמעון's Yosef ben Shimon wife produces
it, they're not going to say wait, wait, there's two יוסף בן
שמעוןs Yosef ben Shimon who live in this town, you know, bring
the witnesses, because there aren't two יוסף בן שמעוןs Yosef ben Shimon
who live in this town, right? In Vilna there's only one יוסף
בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. But he's managed to trick a סופר
sofer and witnesses in a different town to write a גט get
under the name of יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. All right?
So I mean, again, the basic point here is why do we
let somebody get a גט get written without doing the whole proceedings
of the גט get in our presence? Okay, that's really the alternative.
Because the alternative is you have to get the whole proceedings... nowadays
of course we do that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: ומיחזי
ליה שמה ביוסף בן שמעון וכתב גיטא וממטי ליה לאיתתא דהאיך, Umichzei
lei shemeih beYosef ben Shimon vekhateiv gita umamtei lei le'itteta de'haich, brings
it to the other man's wife. אמר ליה רב הונא בר חיננא
הכי אמר רב כל שוחזק שמו בעיר שלושים יום אין חוששין לו.
Amar lei Rav Huna bar Chinana hachi amar Rav kol shehuchzak shemo
ba'ir shloshim yom ein chosheshin lo. No,
he has to have thirty days that that's known, you know, been
in the town and known that that's his name. Now what does
that preclude? So he'll wait thirty days till that's known that that's
his name. So what the רשבם Rashbam says is that by that
time word will get back to the other town or whatever. Like
people... if you do a ruse that you can get it all
done within a day or so, you'll do it. But if you
have to hang around for thirty days, you're giving yourself a lot
of opportunity for exposure and for people finding out. And therefore we're
not concerned that that will be the case. Okay, so is it
possible somebody could do this and get away with it? Sure, but
we're not concerned about it.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara has the following question: לא איתחזק
מאי? Lo itchazak mai?
Let's say some guy comes to the town
and, you know, he hasn't been here thirty days. What do we
do? How do we know what his name is? And now he
asks us to write a גט get for his wife. How do
we know what his name is? So the גמרא Gemara says...
I've got a question. We just learned it's got to be thirty...
oh yeah, you haven't been here long enough. So the answer could
be we don't write a גט get for your wife. The גמרא
Gemara is exploring is there an alternative? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר אביי דקרו ליה
ועני. Amar Abaye dekaru lei ve'ani. So he's walking down the street,
when he got an עליה aliyah he said my name is יוסף
בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. Okay, so now we're going to test
it out. Okay, so there he is, he's in line, he's walking
in front of you in the street and say יוסף Yosef and
you see if he turns around. So that's not a bad test,
right? Because people it's very deeply ingrained when you hear your name
to
like if you're asleep and you hear your name, it's somehow very
deep. But if it's a fake name, we assume you won't turn
around. So let's do the test, okay? And it's a good way
to test if this is the right guy. So the גמרא Gemara
says, רב זביד אמר רמאי ברמאותיה זהיר. Rav Zvid amar ramai beramutei
zahir. No, no, no. These deceivers are very good at their deception.
They'll know to turn around when they hear their name. They're working
on it pretty hard. Okay. So therefore it's not going to be
a good test and the answer is yeah you can't write a
גט get for a guy until he's been around for 30 days.
אי הכי נמי. Ei hachi nami. Okay. ההוא תברא דהוה חתים עליה
רב ירמיה בר אבא. Hahu tavra dehavah chatim alei Rav Yirmeyah bar
Abba.
So there was a certain שובר, shovar, right? תברא Tavra is the
Aramaic word for שובר. shovar. שובר Shovar means like לשבור, lishbor, to
break, it breaks the debt. Okay. So there was a certain receipt
that רב ירמיה בר אבא Rav Yirmeyah bar Abba had signed. אתיא
לקמיה דההיא איתתא. Atya lekamei dehahi itata.
Now again, he was the דיין dayan of a case or something
that he had signed. It seems like that's okay, like there's not
a problem of אין עד נעשה דיין ein ed na'aseh dayan to
be a judge on a document that you yourself had signed. So
a certain woman came to him,
and her husband said look, she paid me my כתובה. kesubah. Here's
the receipt, okay? And you רב ירמיה Rav Yirmeyah you yourself have
signed it. אמרה ליה, Amrah lei, so she said to רב ירמיה,
Rav Yirmeyah, לאו אנא הואי. lav ana havai. No,
that was some other woman who was faking to be me when
you signed it. That woman wasn't me. So yeah, you signed some
woman's receipt for my husband, okay? Or she claimed to be my
husband's wife, she claimed to be me, but it was all a
ruse. It wasn't me. Okay. So אמר אנא נמי אמרי להו לאו
איהי. Amar ana nami amri lehu lav ihi.
You know what? He said, I said to my co-signing witnesses, apparently
like right now in the בית דין beis din it sounds like,
not back then. It sounds like he's saying like right now, I
said, she doesn't seem to be the same woman from that receipt
that we signed like a six months ago or a year ago
or 10 years ago, whenever it was. Okay. So actually I thought
the same thing that you weren't the same woman. But ואמרו לי,
ve'amru li, but they said back to me, מכחשי דכחשא. mikhashi dekhachsha.
No, no, no, no, she's just gotten old, okay? ובגרא לה קלה,
uvagra lah kalah,
and her voice has gotten thick. So it is the same woman
whose receipt we all signed together, okay? She's lying. It is the
same woman. But it does you think it's not because she has
she's changed or whatever, she's gotten older. Okay. So basically what do
we so now the question is, has what's the status? רב פפא
Rav Papa goes into this because you're this case about a person
retracting and almost like retracting twice, right? He had signed, he claimed
that his signature was not valid essentially, that he had been deceived,
or that it was for a different woman or whatever. And then
it sounds like at least the way the story goes it's implicit,
not necessarily explicit, that after the co-witnesses explained it to him, he
retracted his retraction. Okay, he recognized oh maybe it is my signature
or whatever, or maybe this
genuinely is this woman. Okay. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי
Abaye said, אף על גב דאמור רבנן, af al gav de'amur rabanan,
even though the rabbis said, כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד, keivan
shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid, that you're not allowed to retract. And
which now again the question is which retraction are we talking about?
The way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it, we're talking about the retraction
where he him retracting saying you're a different woman. Now that these
other co-witnesses have explained it to him, he realized, oh, okay, so
it's the same woman. Okay. So sort of retracting his so it's
the final retraction. So we should not allow him to retract his
claim that this is a different woman, okay? We should not allow
him to retract his claim that it's a different woman. So צורבא
מרבנן לאו אורחיה למידק. tzurba merabanan lav orchei lemidak.
But
you know, תורה Torah students don't pay attention don't look at women
so much and they don't pay attention to women. So he what
basically maybe he wasn't even looking at her, you noticed, he was
only going by her voice, right? So maybe the other witnesses said,
no, no, no, if you would look at her you would see
she's the same woman. You're just he says I'm not looking at
any women. I'm just listening to her voice and it's a different
voice. Okay. So basically meaning we can understand
why he actually was mistaken because he wasn't actually looking at her,
he was just listening to her voice and therefore we will accept
the final retraction because we there's good circumstantial evidence to support the
idea that he was making a mistake when he thought it was
a different woman. He was listening to her voice? Right. Now, of
course the funny thing here is, I mean there's a couple of
funny things. But I mean, but does everybody get the scenario? Meaning
when he came in front of בית דין Beis Din and he
said, "Oh, this is a different woman," and then he was like,
"No, no, fine, I believe you, it's the same woman," we allow
it? We allow his saying fine, it's the same woman, because we
say when he said it was a different woman, he was misled,
he was only listening to the voice, and he wasn't actually looking
at her, and we understand why he could have been misled.
So, so there's two questions here. Question number one is, since when
is this formal principle of כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד Kivan
shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid reassessed based on circumstantial evidence? Like, what
does that mean? So does that mean in other scenarios where I
retract my statement if it's good circumstantial evidence to explain how that
error came about and how whatever, you would believe me? Meaning, we've
always been brought up to believe, brought up whatever, that this כיון
שהגיד Kivan shehigid is a very formalistic principle, right? Once it's accepted
in בית דין, Beis Din, it doesn't matter how much evidence we
have that, you know, you were, you know, making a mistake or
whatever, like you can't change your testimony. So like, that's question number
one. Who cares that now that it actually is good supporting evidence?
Isn't it supposed to be an ironclad rule? The other question of
course that Eli asks is, which I would like to ask as
well, is why do we accept his first retraction? Right, even if
he had stood by his claim that it's a different woman, why
is that good? We've got, you know, signatures on a שטר. shtar.
So, this is very vague to me how any of this works,
and part of it might have to deal with the fact that
signatures on a שטר shtar are not the same as testimony in
בית דין, Beis Din, right? And is it מקוים mukyum or is
it not מקוים? mukyum? Is it הגיד higid yet? Has he been
מקיים mkayem it? When he said it was a... right, and when
he said like, "It's a different woman," was that really a עדות
edus or was that his ruling as a בית דין? Beis Din?
So it's very vaguey, like, a) why are we... why does it
seem like we would go by the first retraction? Why isn't that
a problem of כיון שהגיד? Kivan shehigid? And since when can you
override the rule of כיון שהגיד Kivan shehigid based on circumstantial evidence?
So, there's a lot here that's not clear, but some of it
certainly has to do with the fact that it's not formal testimony
in a court, it's based on the validity of signatures on a
שטר, shtar, but there's obviously more that needs to be sort of
figured out and unpacked here. All right, we'll end with that.
Any interest tomorrow to...